翻译校对       Mam
日  听      大海
日听校对       Syura
翻译        墨墨
时间轴       黑猫与牛奶
压制      娜夏
OP&ED       葉隠
Syura
诸神字幕组
The Otoris descend from an historic,
princely lineage.
鳳家は由緒ある公爵家の血筋だ
Since the adoption of
the zaibatsu system, long ago,
財閥体制の昔より　医療分野に進出　頭角を現す
we have advanced the medical field,
and distinguished ourselves...
現在も病院経営を核とし
Today as well, with hospital
administration at our core,
we are among the leaders
in the health business.
ヘルスビジネス界の雄とされている
In choosing a successor...
後継者に選ぶ　在学中の首席キープなどは
Keeping yourself at the head of
the class while you're in school
お前の兄たちもこなしてきたことだ
is an accomplishment that
your brothers have achieved.
You must know that it will take
more than that to satisfy me.
わたしがもうそれぐらいで満足しないことは分かっているはずだな
Kyoya, I just had an incredible idea!
鏡夜　すごいこと考え付いたぞ
Where am I?
"A crowd of commoners,
as far as the eye can see"
ここは　どこだ
ママ　早く　こっちだよ
Mama, hurry! This way!
Okay, okay.
I was at home, sleeping,
until just a moment ago...
ついさっきまで家で寝ていたはずでは
Wait, no I wasn't...
いや　違うな　環が何か叫んでいたような
Tamaki was shouting about something...
As I remember, it was about going
to some kind of exhibit or something...
確か何とか展に行くとかどうとか
"Hometown Regional Products Expo"
Doesn't that sound interesting, Kyoya?
おもしろそうだろう　鏡夜
The underprivileged commoners
hold special events
貧しい庶民は　度々こうした催し物を開いては
like this once in a while,
to ease the emptiness
of being unable to travel.
旅行に行けない虚しさを癒していると言う
"One hour earlier"
"Hometown Regional Products Expo"
"Bonmal Department Store"
"4F, Special Expo Hall"
By obtaining notable products
from different regions,
各地の名産品を手にすることで
they are able to somewhat
enjoy the feeling of traveling.
少しでも旅行気分を味わおうというわけだ
So, I've come up with a project,
so that beginning 2nd term,
そこでわれわれは庶民文化を身をもって体感し
we'll be better able as a club
to understand Haruhi's feelings
二学期からは　ハルヒの心情をより理解して
部活に望むというプロジェクトを立ち上げた
by going to experience some
commoners' culture for ourselves.
So, with that in mind, come on,
let's go! Let's go right now!
そういうわけで
さあ行こう　すぐ行こう
Oh, by the way, in keeping with
the purpose of this project,
ちなみに　プロジェクトの目的に合わせて
Haruhi will not be participating
with us today, so if you don't mind...
きょうはハルヒは不参加だから　よろしく
"Grouchy riser"
Come on, come on. You think
you can sleep until almost noon
夏休み最後の日に　昼近くまで寝ていていいと思ってるのか
on the last day of summer vacation?
Let me tell you, I didn't go to bed
until 5 in the morning.
言っておくが　俺が寝たのは明け方五時だ
And who gave you permission
to come into my bedroom, anyhow?
大体誰の許可を得て人の寝室に上がり込んでる
"Hypotensive evil lord"
Kyo-chan is really grouchy
when he wakes up, huh?
鏡ちゃんって　すごく寝起きが悪いんだね
Don't go casting stones.
お前が言うな
"Hypotensive beast"
Huh? What?
"Also a grouchy riser,
though a slightly earlier one"
え　なーに？
Who cares about commoners' culture?
何が庶民文化だ
I'm starting to get pretty tired
of the whole "commoner" shtick.
庶民ネタはいい加減飽きが来てるんだよ　このマンネリ人間め
Formulaic morons. If you want to go,
then suit yourselves.
行きたきゃ勝手にしろ
You're sure we can suit ourselves?
勝手にしていいのか
All right, we've gotten the
hypotensive devil's permission!
よし　低血圧魔王様のお許しが出たぞ
Gentlemen, let's get this devil
dressed up and taken to the car!
皆の衆　魔王様をお着替えさせ　お車にお連れするのだ
Quickly, that one...
no, not this one... yes, that one...
早くしろ　そっち　あっ違う　そっちじゃない　そう　そっち
"Commoners' department store"
Amazing! Look at that!
すごいよ　見てよ
Looks like they're selling a lot
of the same kind of clothing!
なんか　おんなじ服いっぱい売ってんの
Mass-production! Mass-production!
大量生産だ　大量生産だ
Hold on! They have a pet shop!
We're going to the pet shop first!
待て待て　ペットショップがある
まず　ペットショップに行くのだ
I'm going to eat ice cream on the roof!
屋上でアイス食べる～
Oh! Looks like they're holding
some kind of amazing event on the roof!
屋上で何かすごいイベントをやるようだぞ
What is it!?
Ice cream! Ice cream! Ice cream!
アイス…
皆の衆行くぞ　よし　ついてこい
"And so..."
"when the hypotensive evil lord
finally woke up..."
"he realized that he was all alone..."
Oh, so that's it.
なるほど　そういうわけか
I'm currently at the Izumi shopping center.
現在地は泉商店街　歩いて帰れる距離じゃないな
That's not within walking distance of home.
I guess I'll call, and have a car sent out.
電話して車を回させるか
"without his wallet or cell phone..."
"and he was very hungry"
I'm sorry.
ごめんなさい
"Doctor Namahage!"
ママ～
Mama!
I swear, I'm going to kill Tamaki.
環のやつめ　絶対に殺す
Huh? Kyoya- senpai?
あれ　鏡夜先輩
What are you doing here?
なんでこんなところに
Haruhi, how much money do you have on you?
ハルヒ　所持金はいくらだ
Huh?
Kyoya- senpai, are you sure
you're okay with eating here?
鏡夜先輩　本当にこんなところでいいんですか？
There is a restaurant upstairs, as well.
上に一応レストランもありますけど
You don't have very much on you,
so we have little choice.
お前の手持ちが少ないんだから　仕方ないだろう
Oh, make sure to get a receipt.
領収証はもらっておけよ
I'm going to make Tamaki
pay you back tenfold later.
後で環に十倍返しさせる
Ah, I wish I hadn't come.
I just wanted to take a peek
あ～来なきゃよかった
ちょっと物産展を覗こうと思っただけなのに
at the products expo.
Why'd I have to run into Kyoya-senpai?
なんで鏡夜先輩と
What's worse, he's in an awfully foul mood.
しかも目茶目茶機嫌悪いし
Haruhi, how do you place your order here?
ハルヒ　どうやって注文するんだ
I'll do the ordering,
so what would you like?
自分が頼みますから　何がいいですか？
Anything's fine. Just make sure
there's lots of it.
なんでもいい　量の多いのにしてくれ
Okay then, this one,
this one, and some fries.
じゃ　これとこれ　あと　ポテト
まあ～美形　あたし好み
My, he's handsome.
Just my type.
Welcome, can I recommend
our new dessert, as well?
いらっしゃいませ
新商品のデザートもお勧めしておりますが
Nah, I don't need anything sweet.
いや　甘い物は結構
クールだわ　ますますわたし好み
He's so cool.
I'm liking him more and more.
Well then, we also have a new shake here...
それなら　こちら　新作シェイクなどは
"Sweet Sweet Shake
50% more sugar!"
I said I didn't want anything.
いらないと言っている
Excuse me, I need a receipt, please.
すいません　領収証ください
Kyoya- senpai...
鏡夜先輩　いくら機嫌が悪いからって
Just because you might be in a bad mood,
you could have told her
some other way, right?
もうちょっとこう…言い方があるでしょう
She was only doing her job.
向こうもお仕事なんだし
Giving excessive service isn't necessarily
過剰なサービスが正しい接客とは限らんだろう
the right way to wait on customers.
What?
なんだ
Nothing. I was just thinking that
you were eating with unexpected gusto.
あっいえ　意外に豪快に食べるなあと思って
I pictured you eating
in a more refined manner,
もっと上品に食べるイメージがあったし
and thinking that this stuff
wouldn't be to your liking.
こういうのはお口に合わないかと
It isn't particularly to my liking.
別に口には合わないが
Are you saying that I'm so callous
a person as to complain,
奢ってもらって文句を言うほど　非道な人間だと
even when someone else is buying?
No...
いい～え
思ってますけど
I am thinking it, though.
The selling point of this stuff
is that you eat it with your fingers,
大体こういうものは
手づかみで素早く食べられるのが売りだろう
and can eat it fast, right?
It's obvious that following that course
その方針に従って食べるのが一番うまいに決まってる
when eating it will make it taste best.
Besides, it doesn't matter whether
I eat it in a refined manner or not,
それに上品だろうが下品だろうが
since there's no need to worry
about how anyone will view me here.
ここでは誰の目も気にする必要がないからな
I guess in the world of the rich,
やっぱりお金持ちの世界って
マナーとかそう言うプレッシャーがあるのかな
there must be pressure
over manners and so on.
Hey,
for the record, I mean that
it doesn't gain me anything
言っとくが　こんなところで上品振っても
to act all high-class
in a place like this.
何のメリットもないって意味だぞ
There's nothing in it for me to observe
proprieties with you, either.
お前に礼を尽くしても　なんの利益もないだろう
はーそうですか　そうですよね
Oh, you don't say. I suppose not, huh?
Hey, look. That boy
in the glasses is pretty hot.
ねね　見て　あのめがねの子　格好いいよ
- Wow, you're right.
はあ～本当～
Excuse me, is this taken?
すいません　ここ空いてますか
And if you're not using this chair,
could we borrow it?
それと　このいす　使わなければ　お借りしたいんですけど
Go ahead.
どうぞ
Yay, thank you so much!
ありがとうございま～す
No, not at all.
いえ　べつに
Does he really get this indifferent
if there's nothing in it for him?
利益がないと　こうまで無関心になれるものなのか
He's completely different from usual.
普段と全然違う
"When it's in his interest"
Welcome.
いらっしゃいませ
He's far different from Tamaki-senpai,
who's a natural host.
天然ホストみたいな環先輩とは大違いだな
Why do they get along so well?
何で仲がいいんだろう
If you're wondering why Tamaki
and I get along so well...
何故環なんかと仲がいいかと聞かれれば
H- he's completely reading my thoughts!
かん…完全に思考を読まれてる
He's on a telepathic level now...
もはやテレパシーレベル
...the answer is simple.
答えは簡単だ
Because it's in my interest.
I won't act for any other reason.
利益があるからだよ
俺はそれ以外の理由じゃ動かない
I'm an egoist, after all.
エゴイストだからな
Tamaki- senpai would cry
if he heard you say that.
環先輩が聞いたら泣きますよ
No he wouldn't.
泣かないさ
He's known that from the beginning.
It's why we teamed up.
あいつは最初から知ってる　その上で手を組んだ
Hikaru and Kaoru, and even
Honey- senpai and Mori- senpai,
光や馨　ハニー先輩やモリ先輩ですら
we all hang together because
it's in each other's interests to do so.
俺たちはまず　互いへの利益があってこそつるんでいる
Our relationship with
each other's families,
お互いの家の関係や　そこで各人が置かれてる事情とか
and the situations that
each of us are placed in-
well, let's just say that
there's still a lot that you don't know.
まっ　まだまだお前の知らないことが色々あるってことだ
Well, that fool Tamaki sometimes acts
when there's nothing in it for him.
まあ環の馬鹿は　時々利益がなくても行動しているがな
確かに俺と環は　一ミリも同じところがないな
It is true, there isn't a
single millimeter of similarity
between Tamaki and myself.
"Hometown Regional Products Expo"
Senpai, I thought you were
going to take a taxi home.
先輩　タクシーで帰るんじゃなかったんですか
I'm already here, so I'm going
to look around a little first.
せっかくだから　すこし見学していくさ
Hmm, black pearls from
Ishigaki Island, huh?
石垣島の黒真珠か
Those are high quality articles.
上物だな
Will there be any buyers,
in a place like this?
こんなところで買い手が着くのか
Wow, that's amazing. You can tell?
すごいですね　分かるんですか
Such is the education that I've received.
そういう教育を受けている
I have sensed, of course, that usually,
there's a kind of wall between us...
普段から　当然ある種の壁があるのは感じていたわけだけど
I really don't know anything about
your family and such, Kyoya- senpai.
自分は鏡夜先輩の家のこととか
本当に何も知らないですね
There's really nothing especially
there for you to know about my family.
べつにわざわざお前が知るほどのことでもないさ
うちの家族なんて
Well, that kind of seems
unfair, doesn't it?
なんか　不公平じゃないですか
Unfair?
不公平？
After all, Kyoya- senpai,
when it comes to my family,
だって　鏡夜先輩はうちの家のことは
you've even got a firm grasp on
who my dad's friends from work are.
父の仕事仲間のことまできちんと把握しているのに
It seems kind of unfair.
なんか不公平ですよ
That's an intriguing notion,
in its own way.
それなりに興味深い感想だな
Kyoya- senpai, you have
two older brothers, right?
鏡夜先輩には　お兄さんがふたりいるんですよね
What kind of people are they?
どうな人なんですか？
These three are my sons.
この三人が私の息子たちです
Pleased to make your acquaintance.
どうぞ　よろしく
My, what fine sons you have.
まあ　立派な息子さんたちですこと
They look most promising.
頼もしい限りですな
I truly am envious.
本当に羨ましいね
All three appear to be quite brilliant.
三人ともかなり優秀だし
まっ鳳家を継ぐのは間違えなく長男だろうが
The one to succeed the Otori family
will no doubt be the oldest son.
The youngest son, Kyoya- kun,
had the most impressive looks,
末っ子の鏡夜君　一番ルックスが印象的だったけど
but with three sons, there's no way
he'll be the head of the family,
三男じゃ　どう足掻いても当主にはなれないわね
no matter how hard he tries.
They are exceptional men.
優秀な人たちだよ
Enough so that they meet
Father's expectations without any trouble.
父の期待に無難に応えられるくらいにはね
And so, even more is
expected of the third son.
だから三男にはそれ以上のものが期待される
Keeping yourself at the head
of the class while you're in school
在学中の首席キープなどは　お前の兄たちもこなしてきたことだ
is an accomplishment that
your brothers have achieved.
You must know that it will take
more than that to satisfy me.
私がもうそれくらいで満足しないことは分かっているはずだな
So things really are hard for you, huh?
やっぱり色々大変なんですね
You think so?
そうか
I can't think of any game
more fun than this.
これ以上おもしろいゲームはないと思っているが
Oh, my, pieces by Komatsu Shoin?
まあ　小松匠陰の作品ですの
Imagine, seeing them here.
こんなところで見られるなんて
Madam, you have a sharp eye.
奥さん　お目が高いね
Senpai?
先輩？
Yes, Komatsu Shoin's pieces have
such a nice color, don't they?
そう　小松匠陰は色がいいでしょう
本当言うとね
To tell you the truth,
these are pieces that
I'm not supposed to have here.
こんなところに持ってきていい品じゃないんだけどね
These are valuable items,
which were not supposed to have been had
これは　小松一門が代々門外不出にしてきた貴重なもんなんだよ
outside of the Komatsu family
for generations.
Oh, my...
These are fakes, madam.
贋物ですよ　奥様
W-what did you say? Stop messing around!
You're just a kid.
なん　なんだと　子供のくせに　ふざけんな
It's true, the way the blue comes out here
確かに　この青の出し方は　匠陰のものと酷似していますが
is very similar to Shoin's work,
but an authentic piece would have
a darker gradation around the base,
本物はもっとグラデーションの根元がくすんでますし
and this lacquer is too clear.
塗りも綺麗過ぎる
I'm going to report you
for obstructing my business!
営業妨害で通報してやる
What school do you go to, you delinquent!?
学校はどこだ　この不良め
あ～　やっぱり
Ah, I knew it.
One of the strokes in this
seal on the bottom is off.
底の刻印も　一部のハライが違いますね
If this is authentic,
there should be a certificate.
本物なら証書があるはずです
Shall we do a handwriting analysis on it?
筆跡鑑定にかけましょうか
l-I left it back at my shop today...
きょ　きょうは　店のほうにおいてきて
Ah, in that case,
my family has had dealings
あ～　それでしたら
うちは古くから小松家と交流がありますので
with the Komatsu family going way back,
so I could contact them right now,
and have them verify these.
今すぐ連絡を取って確認させますが
Would that be all right?
よろしいですね
Helping others is something
人助けって言うのは
やっぱり鏡夜先輩にとっても利益なんですよね
that is beneficial to you after all,
isn't it, Kyoya- senpai?
Ah, didn't you know?
お前には分からないか
That woman is the wife of the chairman
of a major electronics maker.
あのご婦人は　大手電気メーカーの会長婦人だよ
This is my first time meeting her, as well,
俺も会うのは初めてだが
but I can tell by looking
at the ring on her left hand.
あの左手の指輪を見て分かった
It's a company that our family
has a lot of dealings with.
うちの家とも取引の多い企業だよ
Imagine, running into one of
the Otori family's boys here.
こんなところで鳳家のお坊ちゃんに会えるなんてね
Are you out incognito, too?
The next chance I get,
あなたもお忍びで？
今度お宅のリゾート施設をぜひ利用させていただくわね
I'll be sure to take advantage
of your family's resort facilities.
I'm honored.
光栄です
Sure enough, Kyoya-senpai can
only be who Kyoya-senpai is.
やっぱり鏡夜先輩は鏡夜先輩でしかないのか
Huh? But earlier...
あれ　だけどさっきは
As I remember it, at the time...
あの時は確か…
Hey, Haruhi, did you know this?
おい　ハルヒ　知ってたか？
Know what?
なんです
Are melons really this popular
among candy makers?
メロンはそんなにお菓子メーカーに人気があるのか？
Huh?
I don't get this.
よく分からんな
Intentionally giving
a corn snack melon flavoring,
コーンスナックをわざとメロンの味にしているのは
even when it's not actually a melon,
実際はメロンでない以上　違和感を感じるだけではないのか
just seems disconsonant, doesn't it?
That's an intriguing notion,
in its own way.
それなりに興味深い感想です
Did I say something funny?
笑うところか
No, it's just that earlier,
you said something
いや　だってさっき一ミリも同じところがないとか言ってたのに
about there not being one millimeter
of similarity between you,
and yet, that sounded like
something Tamaki- senpai would say.
環先輩みたいなこと言ってます
I see.
そっか　確かにこういうのは　環や双子たちが喜びそうだな
This definitely seems
like something that Tamaki
or the twins would be thrilled over.
All right, I'll buy them.
よし　買っていこう
Haruhi, your wallet.
ハルヒ　財布
Oh, right. I'm paying, aren't I?
あーそうだ　自分が払うんでしたね
Y-you're too heavy! You're too heavy!
重い　重いって
Tama-chan, something is about to start!
タマちゃん　何か始まるよ
"Powerful motor"
Hi, everyone!
ハイ～みんな～
The 2nd school term starts tomorrow!
明日から二学期
Have you gotten all of your
summer vacation homework done?
もう夏休みの宿題は　済ませたかな～
え～まだ～
Eh? Not yet?
Then, stop goofing around here!
じゃ　こんなところで遊んでないで　早く帰って宿題やらなきゃ
You need to hurry home
and do your homework!
Why is Renge- kun up there?
何故蓮華君が
Seems like recently...
なんか最近
...she's been spreading out more and more.
ますます手広くやってるな
Children! You naughty boys
and girls who play around
子供たちよ
宿題もせず遊んでる悪い子のお前たちはもう帰れない
instead of doing your homework
can't go home now!
I, Doctor Namahage-sama,
have taken over Bonmal Department Store!
このボンマルデパートはドクターなまはげ様が占拠した
Help me, Ouran Sentai Host Rangers!
助けて　桜蘭戦隊　ホストレンジャー～
That's far enough!
そこまでだ
Oh, you're the shadow leader
of the Host Rangers I've heard about!
お前はホストレンジャーの影のリーダーと噂される
ホ～スト～ブラック！
Host... Black!!
Come to think of it, where is Kyo-chan?
そう言えば　鏡ちゃんは？
Kyoya- senpai...
鏡夜先輩
I'm sure that Tamaki- senpai feels that
環先輩はきっと人助けにも利益を感じると思いますよ
there's something to be
gained by helping others.
That's probably true, for him. Not for me.
あいつはそうだろうな　俺とは違う
Then, what is there for you
to gain, Kyoya- senpai?
じゃ　鏡夜先輩の利益って何なんですか？
Wealth, or fame? Some sort
of actual, tangible gain?
何か具体的に形のある実益？
The way I see it,
Tamaki- senpai feels benefited
環先輩は　自分から見ても
from doing things that
I don't see as having any point.
無駄なことに利益を感じてるなあとはよく思いますが
Kyoya- senpai, I think you're
a lot like Tamaki- senpai.
鏡夜先輩も　環先輩とよく似てると思います
Kyoya,
鏡夜　隣町の公立高校までの地図をこの方に用意して差し上げろ
provide this man a map to the
public school in the next town over.
That girl looked like she wanted
to play together with you.
俺にはあの子がお前と一緒に弾きたがっているように見えたぞ
Having a brother and sister
that don't care for each other,
思いあう兄弟が一緒にいられないなど　あってはならぬ大問題
and who can't be with each other,
is a serious problem that should not be!
Who decided that? You're the one
who's giving up without doing anything!
そんなこと誰が決めた
何もしないうちに諦めてるのは　お前のほうだ
Kyoya, I just had an incredible idea!
鏡夜　すごいこと考え付いたぞ
Let's form a club!
部を立ち上げよう
This is an announcement
for a little lost boy.
迷子のお呼び出しを申し上げます
This is an announcement
for a little lost boy.
迷子のお呼び出しを申し上げます
Otori Kyoya-kun, who is here from Tokyo.
東京都よりお越しの鳳鏡夜君
Otori Kyoya-kun, is lost.
迷子の鳳鏡夜君
His guardian, Suou-sama, is waiting
for him at the 2nd floor counter.
保護者の須王様が二階カウンターでお待ちです
Kyoya-kun is 180cm in height,
鏡夜君は身長百八十センチ
and is wearing glasses.
特徴はめがね
Isn't that the boy?
あの人じゃない
That's the boy.
あの人だよ
As big as he is, he's gotten himself lost?
あんなに大きいのに迷子ですって
Mister, are you all right?
お兄ちゃん　大丈夫？
I am going to kill that idiot.
あの馬鹿
殺す
"Information Desk"
Ohh, Kyoya! You're safe!
鏡夜　無事だったか～
Um, what is Haruhi doing with you?
何でハルヒが一緒にいるんだ
Haru-chan! Haru-chan!
Let's go play together!
ハルちゃんハルちゃん　一緒に遊ぼう
Let's play! Let's play!
遊ぼう～遊ぼう～
No, I'm going home. For some reason,
I'm worn out today.
いいえ　もう帰ります
今日は何だか疲れました
Hey, now!
おい　こら　やめろ　やめろ
Cut that out! Stop licking me!
What's with the dog?
なんだ　その犬は
Isn't she great? I just bought her
at the pet shop up on the roof.
いいだろう　さっき屋上のペットショップで買ったのだ
Hey, cut that out, Antoinette!
やめろ　アントワネット
How are this idiot and I alike?
こんな馬鹿と俺のどこが似ている
Earlier, when you said that you
decided to help out that lady
さっきのご婦人を助けたとき
指輪を見て決めたって言うの
because you saw her ring,
you were lying, huh?
あれ　嘘ですよね
When you first saw that woman,
you couldn't have seen her ring.
最初にあのご婦人を見かけたとき
指輪なんて見えませんでした
There was a flag in front of us, after all.
手前にのぼりがかかってましたから
I just don't understand it.
よく分かりませんね
Senpai, intentionally acting like an egoist,
先輩がわざとエゴイストとして振舞うのは
when you're not actually an egoist,
実際エゴイストでない以上
just seems disconsonant.
違和感を感じます
That's an intriguing notion,
in its own way.
それなりに興味深い感想だ
な　何なんですか　知らない男の子が
W- what is this!? An unfamiliar boy is-
Oh, they're going at it.
お～やってるな
Chika-chan, you still haven't
put in enough practice!
チカちゃん　まだまだ精進が足りないね
Next time, " Chika-kun's 'Down
With Honey' Declaration"
Ouran High School Host Club will
be waiting for you, next week!
桜蘭高校ホストクラブ　来週も
お待ちしております